it is October 23rd
2024 and all eyeses are on the Middle
East right now after we had documents
leaked here in the US coming from the US
intelligence Community specifically
referring to Israel's plan the plan to
attack Iran those documents also notably
confirm the existence of Israel's
nuclear weapons program and I wanted to
talk about all of that I wanted to talk
to an expert in the fields we were able
to do just that but just a quick note
before we get into the interview just a
reminder that I do have a new episode of
sanctioned my exclusive series for paid
subscribers that is out today in this
episode we are doing a deep dive on
Israel's current Siege in Northern Gaza
the fact that it didn't just start in
the last three weeks we are seeing
Israel in a position where it is working
over time to ethnically cleanse the Gaza
Strip of Palestinians we saw a year ago
that they were ordering Palestinians to
leave the northern half of the Gaza
Strip their attempt has been to clear it
of people altoe and that attempt hasn't
worked in the last year so now they're
specifically targeting the remaining
400,000 Palestinians with a new stay and
starve order in which they are literally
looking to starve out nearly half a
million people from this area by cutting
off all food water and Medicine in this
week's episode of sanctioned we took a
look at where things stand now how we
got to this point and of course how
Netanyahu is looking to proceed on the
road to Greater Israel you can find that
episode if you are a paid subscriber
over on my page on substack that's
Rachel bl. substack docomo find it for
paid subscribers on my patreon that's
patreon.com Rachel blevens thank you so
much to all of you who have already
signed up as paid subscribers and
already are joining the community over
there your support truly means the world
and now let's get back to today's
interview over here on the free feed we
talked about the latest when it comes to
the Middle East we also talked a little
bit about the situation in Ukraine when
it comes to us support for Kev and the
question of how long that is going to
continue as well as where things stand
for the media here in the US I know I've
talked a lot about the fact that we've
seen the kind of unofficial official end
of Russian media funding here in the us
as we know it and so we took a look at
the impact of that here in our media
World especially with the upcoming
election we discussed all that and more
earlier so let's take a listen to that
conversation now joining me now to
discuss is John kyaku an author
journalist and former CIA officer and
whistleblower John thanks so much for
taking the time to join me oh thanks
very much Rachel now I want to get your
take on the latest on a few different
topics but I want to start off with
these leaked documents coming from us
intelligence you've got the US saying
it's now investigating after highly
classified documents were leaked and
published on telegram that appeared to
show the pentagon's analysis of Israel's
plan to attack Iran as presented to
Washington's five eyes allies now the
files also notably included the
acknowledgement that Israel has nuclear
weapons which both the US and Israel
won't say public
so how do you view this I mean yes we
all knew that Israel was planning to
attack Iran that that attack supposed to
be coming at some point but how
significant were these files and the
fact that they were leaked this is
extraordinarily uh important for a
couple of reasons first of all every
country every every belligerent in in
this situation has what they call
off-the-shelf plans right so there is
always the skeleton of a plan uh for an
attack whether it's against Iran or Iraq
or the Israelis have it for Lebanon and
Yemen and Iran and everybody has has at
least the shell of an operational
military plan but to have what the
United States is apparently calling the
plan the actual plan and it's presenting
to five eyes is incredibly important
what makes it even even more important
is this apparent acknowledgment that the
Israelis have a nuclear uh bomb now we
we all know that the Israelis have a
nuclear bomb we've known since the 1980s
but this is one of those things that the
United States has never publicly
acknowledged and certainly Israel has
never publicly acknowledged it in fact
uh there was an Israeli whistleblower in
the 1990s who went public with the fact
that Israel has a bomb and um served
most of the rest of his life in an
Israeli
Penitentiary so this is dramatic I just
as as side Rachel I have a friend who uh
a former CIA officer a former Pentagon
uh senior Pentagon um civilian official
who wrote a book in retirement about
Israel and he made one fleeting
reference to um to Israel and he wrote
um Israel's nuclear program those were
the only three words and when he sent
the book to the CIA Publications review
board those were the only words that
were redacted Israel's nuclear program
so now the cat's out of the bag and uh
and that makes this a very big
deal I'll add I'll add one more thing if
you don't mind sure most of the
information that we see come out in
these leaks is classified at the secret
level this because it's nuclear in
nature uh would be classified at the top
secret level so legally the leak would
have to be defined as something causing
what they call grave damage to the
National Security not ours in this case
but Israel's grave damage that's how
important this is wow that is
interesting and I really I appreciate
you breaking it down and really kind of
explaining that because I look at this
and the first thing I think is not is
the Israeli government really scrambling
right now the first thing I think is how
is Netanyahu going to use this to his
Advantage now we know that right now he
can get away with just about whatever he
wants it seems like on the p on the
surface but I also wonder too is there a
chance that Netanyahu takes this and he
goes oh well you can handle this
information and then he uses it to
further get leverage over the US
government or does he have so much
leverage already that it doesn't even
matter at this point how do you see kind
of the situation when it comes to Israel
reaction that's a great question um and
I think the I think it has two answers
so on the one hand this has to just be
infuriating for for Netanyahu and really
for any Israeli government official that
the cat is out of the bag
so there's no upside to Israeli military
Secrets being leaked on the other hand
the answer to your question is yes this
is going to allow Netanyahu to extract
yet more concessions from the United
States you know he's going to be able to
say you couldn't even be trusted with my
nuclear secrets now you owe me whether
you owe me you know assistance in
planning an alternative a carrier battle
group in the Eastern Mediterranean maybe
you handle Yemen while we handle Iraq or
I'm sorry Iran and Lebanon whatever it
is it's going to embolden him to ask for
yet more yeah and I think that that's uh
something the US is probably well
scrambling on certainly I did think it
was interesting that when it comes to
those Anonymous us sources that are then
being quoted reacting to this you
haven't heard anyone saying oh no you
know kind of downplaying it being like
Oh those documents weren't real right
those were just drawn up instead it's
the thing of oh yeah we're we're
investigating that right we're we're
dealing with it on our end that's right
and also curious to when it comes to
Israel's plan right the plan to attack
Iran the fact that we've kind of had
these you know Anonymous us officials
again who have been speaking out in
recent weeks saying there's going to be
an attack it's going to likely happen
before election day here in the US which
is coming up in just a couple of weeks
so how do you view how far the US is
willing to let this go in terms of
expanding to a full-on war with Iran I
mean it it seems like the Biden
Administration right they'll they will
allow a full-on genocide in Gaza they
will allow the killing of hundreds of
civilians in Lebanon but when it comes
to war with Iran that's been the one
thing that they've been like okay let's
be a little bit careful here does it
seem like they're getting to that point
is this just about waiting until getting
really through the upcoming election
that's that's a tough one to answer I I
think in part it's about getting through
the election but Netanyahu is going to
be focused almost solely on on on
offense right he's got an ongoing War
genocide in Gaza he has an ongoing war
in Lebanon we learned just yesterday
that the Israelis killed the new uh
leader of Hezbollah we didn't even
really know his name very very well here
in the United States he had only been
the head of his Bala for what a week a
week and a half maybe um but all eyes
are on Iran and the question at least
the question being posed in the in the
The Press here in the United States is
do the Israelis hit Iranian economic
targets because thanks to the jcpoa and
the opening of trade relations between
Iran and Europe under the jcpoa the
economy is actually pretty good right
now do the Israelis hit military targets
most likely or do the Israelis hit
nuclear targets now we know that most of
the nuclear Targets in Iran that are
worth hitting are deep
underground bunker Buster bombs might
get some of them the Israelis don't have
those bunker Busters we
do or do the Israelis use nukes to get
to them the conventional wisdom right
now at least what's being reported in
the American Media uh is that the
Israelis are going to go after uh
Iranian military targets they're not
going to go after the economy they're
not going to go after the nukes and
they're not going to Target civilians
because public opinion is already a
problem for the Israelis International
public opinion so I think that's what we
should expect to see and I think it's
going to be um a tough attack in that
they're not going to foot around
and just you know launch a couple of
missiles into into military airport
runways to make it difficult for a plane
to take off I think we're looking at a
pretty heavy attack coming up yeah and
especially as more time passes right
there's more of a buildup now you've got
these League documents out there and I'm
also curious too because I know that
when it comes to Iran when they
initially retaliated against Israel on
the 1 of October they had said look if
you respond to us we are going to keep
escalating right this is going to get
very bad they put that warning out there
ever since there's been some back and
forth of is the US have have they been
able to talk to Iran to kind of calm
them down a little bit to get them to
allow some sort of response from Israel
but given all of the assassinations
Israel has carried out since then how do
you see the position that Iran is in
right now and what they could do if
Israel does carry out those attacks on
Military targets yeah this is a tough
one you know everybody really uh that at
least everybody that I know lauded the
patience that Iran showed U after Ismael
hunia was killed in an Israeli attack in
Teran right they they blew up the guest
house in which he was staying he was the
lead uh negotiator uh for Hamas and this
was an attack on Iranian uh soil
violation of Iranian sovereignty the
Iranians
responded by launching drones but they
were slow drones and the Iranians warned
the jordanians and warned the Americans
and warned the British that these drones
were coming it took them six hours to to
reach Israel and seven got through there
was no damage the Israeli Iron Dome shot
down hundreds of them so it was a show
of force but nothing really came of it
and everybody said okay the Iranians
saved face they didn't do any damage
that's going to be the end of it it
wasn't the end of it the the Israelis
are provocative they continue to be
provocative against the Iranians and so
we we've gotten to the point now with
the assass assination of um of
hella where the Iranians had to respond
now they did respond it was tougher than
it was with the initial drone attack now
the Israelis are going to respond again
you're you're probably a little too
young to remember a Bugs Bunny cartoon
but our former our our former colleague
um Wimer Leon and I were talking about
this the other day where there's this
famous cartoon it's from the 50s and um
Bugs Bunny and um yed Sam are fighting
and one punches the other the other
pulls out a knife the other pulls out a
gun the other pulls out a cannon they
get to the point where their their the
world is is uh in between the two of
them one's on one side of the world
one's on the other and they use nuclear
weapons against each other right so it
was this very quick um worsening in the
situation that's what we're seeing right
now
between Israel and Iran okay you killed
a guy in our country we're going to send
some slow motion drones then the
Israelis kill Hass asala okay now we're
going to use missiles then the Israelis
respond we're going to hit your military
so what's the response from Iran going
to be it's going to have to be tougher
and one of the things that we're not
hearing in the media right now is what
if the Iranians respond but not in
Israel not on the battlefield what
happens if the Iranians blow up an
Israeli Embassy somewhere or a a Jewish
uh you know Community Center or
somewhere or attack a hotel that is you
know frequented by by
Jews it's something that we haven't
considered and so you know we're frankly
not sure how bad this thing can get yeah
that I hadn't considered that either I
mean I think I was so focused on okay
it's going to be the back and forth
between the two of them but yeah it does
make wonder and we also have the US with
troops quite literally all around the
world is you know sitting ducks in
various places and so a lot of concerns
there and I also wonder too you know
looking at this from the perspective of
an American we're going okay we know
that for the US government no matter
which party is in office they are going
to go above and beyond for Israel it
doesn't matter if Israel is carrying out
an all out genocide of the Palestinians
the US will be there to support them and
to make it possible
but that's not the only place in the
world that the US is meddling or is
sending tro well I should say weapons
and ammunition to maybe not troops just
yet at least officially they also were
quite busy over in Ukraine right and you
have this situation where the us at
least under the Biden Administration
they have given Ukraine so much support
to the point where they're literally on
the road to World War III against Russia
now you have at least one of the
candidates and in the upcoming election
claiming he's going to stop this war now
whe whether you believe him or not is
another story right but how do you view
the current state of us support for
Ukraine and how that plays a role in
really what we as a country can handle
at this point because we have all of
these different fires going on in the
world that we help set and that we help
make bigger and yet the US is acting
like we've got everything and
everything's fine there was an article
in the Washington Post a couple of days
ago saying that talk of uh of a
potential peace agreement between Russia
and Ukraine is an invention of the
American political system and it is
meant solely for American public opinion
and I think that's true but the reason
that I believe this conflict is almost
over is because the Republican party
here in the United States has made a
decision that it will not support a
blank check for Ukraine this war has
been going on now for coming up on three
years and it's essentially a
stalemate I think what we're going to
end up seeing is Congress refusing to
play along any longer I should I should
even be more specific republicans in
Congress refusing to play along the
conventional wisdom is that the
Republicans are going to retake control
of the uh Senate even if the Democrats
take control of the house
uh you can't get legislation through
without agreement from both
parties and there just is not agreement
on continued Aid to Ukraine if Donald
Trump is elected president forget it the
whole thing's over literally it's over
you know
overnight um even if even if kamla
Harris wins I don't think she'll be able
to get um continued Ukraine Aid through
a Republican Senate and so I think that
it's beyond time to let the diplomats do
what they're paid to do and negotiate an
agreement and my guess is that that
agreement is going to be exactly what
the Russians had proposed in
2022 that they keep uh donet and luhansk
of course they keep
Crimea uh and Ukraine does not enter
NATO I don't think the Russians care if
Ukraine joins the European Union but
they do not want yet another NATO
country on their border I think that's
what we're going to see probably sooner
rather than later all right to play
Devil's Advocate just a little bit here
because I may be a bit more cynical I
did see and this was several weeks ago
now Mr Mike Pompeo came out and he said
don't worry if Trump gets in office
right he was still plenty supportive of
Ukraine when he was in office he's not
Joe Biden sure but he still supported
them we'll make sure that there is
someone in his ear to make sure that
Ukraine still gets support from the US
now you look at Trump you look at what
he said you look at even his running
mate JD Vance JD Vance has said we need
to stop giving money to Ukraine right we
need some accountability there so do you
think that a possible second Trump
Administration is bulletproof or is
there con some concern about some swamp
creatures still being a part of his
cabinet that are able to get in his ear
and say Hey you know Mr Putin he's not
giving you everything you want or he's
not taking your calls or whatever that
thing may be that kind of talks right to
Trump's ego and makes him say okay we'll
continue on in this way or has he
learned more than I'm giving him credit
for well Donald Trump is notoriously
poor at uh at choosing people with with
uh whom to surround himself um you're
right about Mike Pompeo Mike Pompeo is a
swamp creature here in Washington M Mike
Pompeo is very much a Cheney
neoconservative as was John Bolton so
Trump does have a poor track record of
saying the right things when it comes to
a more isolationist foreign policy and
then appointing neocons who never saw
War they didn't want to jump into with
both feet but JD Vance is not Mike Pence
and Mike Pompeo is not going to be
Secretary of State and Republicans on
Capitol Hill are far more public now
than they were four years ago about
Ukraine I think that Trump is going to
wield far more Authority on foreign
policy than he wielded in his first term
because he allowed himself in the first
term to be influenced by
neoconservatives like John Bolton and
they're just not going to be around
anymore yeah and I I hope that that's
the case right I think I I look at him
and I go okay exactly as you said look
you were influenced in your first term
right you allowed this to be your
cabinet you have to learn from that and
you have to do better if you get that
second shot in the white house now
that's right speaking of the upcoming
election I know that one of the
conversations that has been had it was
interesting we we went through Russia
gate in 2016 2020 rolled around and all
of a sudden you've literally had the US
intelligence Community days after the
2020 election going no foreign
interference everything's fine right we
figured everything out and then come
2024 and all of sudden you've got us
intelligence officials already warning
that both Russia and Iran may try to
incite postelection violence now this is
an unclassified assessment that was
released today that says the rather
released on Tuesday that says the US
intelligence Community is increasingly
confident that Russian actors are
considering and in some cases
implementing a broad range of influence
efforts timed with the election some of
these are aimed at inciting violence and
calling into question the validity of
democracy as a political system
regardless of who wins this may be a new
one right it's not just oh they're Pro
Trump they're Pro Biden or Harris now
it's just our political system as a
whole how do you view These Warnings and
how seriously we should be taking them
well I think that the warnings are
probably
true on the one hand and on the other
hand I don't think we should take them
seriously and I I'll tell you why we
always do this to other countries always
uh other countries always do this to us
it's just a reality of life in the 21st
century or in the 20th century it
happened all the time I I read something
recently about uh this warning that the
Russians or that that organizations
connect connected to Russia were uh
taking out Facebook ads in Pennsylvania
okay probably true but guess what
Facebook said that they were able to
trace $30 worth of ads in the state of
Pennsylvania $30 so okay let's say that
it's true who cares it's not going to
amount to anything there was a report
that came out yesterday that this this
phony report about Tim
Walls you know grooming some young guy
for sex or whatever uh it turned out
that the guy had his identity stolen and
he didn't know anything anything about
it he's never met Tim Walls he never
studied under Tim Walls Tim Walls was
not his coach this may have been a
Russian operation okay let's assume it
was a Russian operation what's the
damage there's none because nobody cares
the me the mainstream media never picked
up this stupid story and the alternative
media that did pick it up made it sound
so stupid and so foolish that nobody
took it
seriously so you know this is just this
is just a reality that we live in in the
in the digital age where there are going
to be foreign intelligence actors
meddling like this and those foreign
intelligence actors include the United
States we medal like this I'll give you
one other example I used to be the chief
investigator at the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee uh when uh 2009 to
2012 and um I went to Afghanistan to do
a study on the heroin poppy crop
and I concluded that this was a serious
problem because at the time Afghanistan
was producing 93% of the world's
heroin well then I was told you might
not want to publish this study because
we want Afghanistan to produce 93% of
the world's heroin because almost all of
that heroin goes to Russia and Iran and
we want them to be addicted to heroin
because it weakens their societies
well it's the same thing
today right they want to interfere in
our elections because it causes a little
bit of chaos and perhaps it weakens us
that's just a reality of the way the
world works today yeah and I really want
to know if anyone's vote if anyone's
mind at all are their opinion on any
issue has ever been changed by a
Facebook ad right whether exactly
Hillary Clinton Harris Trump I don't
care I want to know if you were out
there reach out to me and let me know
because yeah it's it's mindboggling to
think and I know the US always tries to
act like they have the upper hand right
how dare anyone else have any sort of
whether it's Facebook ads whether it's
direct meddling or you know putting out
stories that may cause people to be like
oh well that I didn't know that about
Tim Walls and of course that's also the
concern too is are people going to do
their own research but I guess that's
also up to the people right if you hear
a story about Tim Walls are you taking
the second step to look further into
that to see what are the actual sources
where did this come from is it
corroborated by multiple different
sources lastly what are your concerns
when it comes to the American people
where we stand and also how complacent
we have become in some ways when it
comes to our news media and what we just
ultimately believe if it kind of fits
into our Echo chamber of where our
political belief
stand I'm worried about that Rachel I
don't know if you saw any of the um the
media reports related to the demise of
our former Outlet uh Sputnik you and I
were colleagues of course at sputnick uh
it it wasn't very widely reported but
there were a couple of radio oriented uh
journals that said that we had been shut
down and they they celebrated the fact
that we were shut down and they
criticized us they criticized You by
name as a matter of fact uh because they
said that uh you spent some of the time
in your last show talking about the
so-called genocide in
Palestine so yes I did yeah so my my
point is we were the only ones talking
about the the genocide in Palestine we
were the only ones talking about human
rights and now we're gone we're not on
the air and people can't have access to
an independent voice on Foreign Affairs
and politics or whatever it else
whatever else it is that we were talking
about
um that's not the American way our media
today uh is just an echo
chamber where you know you can Tinker
around the edges there are little
differences between you know Fox and CNN
and MSNBC I suppose but if you want an
alternative voice in America you can't
get it I used to watch Al jazer um every
day every single day not all day but I
would switch I I I watch all the
networks and I include Fox and CNN and
MSNBC and BBC and um Al jazer and
whatever else I could get on my on my
provider well aler is gone it's just
gone you can't watch it anymore you
can't watch RT anymore here in the
United States it just doesn't exist you
can watch BBC which just Echoes what you
see on
CNN but that's it if you want an
alternative voice you're of luck it
doesn't exist and so this this is bad
for America because it doesn't give both
sides of every story it doesn't help to
educate or inform Americans so that
Americans can make an informed decision
in the voting booth or in the newspaper
oped columns or anywhere else we get
only one side we get the American side
the official side and then that's it and
that makes us worse
yeah oh absolutely and that's the thing
is it's like if you don't like if you're
CNN in Fox News you don't like how
popular rch or Sputnik are becoming
instead of looking at their news and
what they're putting out and going okay
what can we do better right what can we
do to bring viewers back to us they're
just like how can we shut down the
opposing side right or not even not even
opposing side but how can we shut down
the other voices out there the
competition that is out there and you
know if if I have to have a final show
and I'm criticized for you know talking
about an ongoing genocide then I will
take that because I don't think that I'm
ever going to look back exactly I don't
think I'm ever going to look back and
think well I wish I hadn't done that or
I wish I hadn't raised awareness about
the Palestinians that were being
slaughtered using weapons that were made
in the USA let me add one other thing
too before we leave um The Washington
Post listened to one of my shows as well
and it was a show uh in which we had a
guest named Paul Wright who's the
founder of the human rights defense
center in Florida it's a it's a
prisoners rights organization we also
had the independent journalist Kevin
gustala and on this uh episode of of my
show on Sputnik we were talking about a
crooked judge in Pennsylvania who had
taken bribes to send children juvenile
Defenders to a private prison so the
private prison makes a a profit when
it's full and it was kicking back some
of the profit to the
judge the Washington Post listened to
that episode and said the next day that
I was weakening our democracy those were
their words I was weakening our
democracy by talking about this issue on
a Russian radio station it wasn't the
judge who was weakening our democracy or
the private prison company incarcerating
children for a profet
I was the
one and it's like you know our media
they just don't get it they just don't
get it yeah they don't even realize that
it's literally what they're saying out
loud right this is the reason that no
one trusts you and that trust in the
media here in the US is that in alltime
low here this year as it should be and
yet another reminder why anyone watching
this be sure if there are any
independent journalists out there
alternative media that you value make
sure that you are following them on all
platforms because as we've seen the big
Tech ones are not safe certainly a lot
of moving Parts here all around and I
really appreciate you taking the time to
join me today to break down all of the
latest John kyaku an author journalist
and former CIA officer and whistleblower
thank you so much for your time and
insight thank you Rachel I want to say
also that it was such a great pleasure
to work with you you are a real
newsperson I wish you the very best
going at alone you deserve success oh
well thank you I appreciate that and I
hope we get to have more of these
conversations I know you have a million
projects going on all at once and so I
look forward to following everything
that you do thank you Rachel if anything
in this video resonated with you be sure
to like it share it with your friends
leave a comment and as always don't
forget to subscribe and if you want to
keep up with all of my work make sure
that you're subscribed to my page on
substack that's Rachel bin. substack
doccom if you want to support my work
you can also check out my page on
patreon that's patreon.com Rachel
blevens that's where you can join the
community there and as always thank you
all so much for all of your support I'll
see you next time